Welcome to the ultimate Django course. In this course, I'm going to teach you everything you need to know about Django from the very basics to more advanced concepts.
So by the end of this course, you'll be able to use Django to build production grade backends for your web and mobile apps.
If you have always wanted to learn web development with Python, you are in the right place.
We'll use Python and Django to build and deploy the backend for an e-commerce application.
If you're looking for a comprehensive, organized, and practical course that takes you from zero to hero and prepares you for the job, this is the right Django course for you.
Everything you need to know about Django is in one place in the right order.
So you don't need to jump back and forth between random tutorials.
I'm Mosh Hamidani, and I've taught millions of people how to advance their software engineering skills through my YouTube channel and online school, quotewithmosh.com.
If you're new here, be sure to subscribe as I upload new videos all the time.
So let's jump in and get started.
Let's talk about what you need to know to take this course.
For starters, you need to know Python. You need to know the basics of Python, as well as object oriented programming concepts such as classes, inheritance, polymorphism, and so on.
You should also know the basics of relational databases, so you should be familiar with concepts such as tables,
columns, primary and foreign keys, relationships, and so on.
If you need to refresh the fundamentals, I have a couple of beginner level tutorials on my YouTube channel, as well as comprehensive courses on my website,
codewithmosh.com. I've put the links down below in case you're interested.
Alright, so I'm assuming that you're the right student for this course, now let's talk about how you should take this course.
First and foremost, I want you to watch this entire course all the way
from the beginning to the end, even if you're familiar with Django, because along the way
I will share a lot of tips and tricks and I don't want you to miss out on any of them.
If you have taken any of my other courses, you know that I'm not going to waste your time
with repetitive or useless stuff, so make sure to watch every lesson.
Now, while watching each lesson, I want you to take notes.
You can just write down some keywords on a piece of paper if you don't want to write a lot of notes.
I strongly believe that the act of writing things down will help you
remember new things that you learn. Then, after each lesson, go through
your notes and repeat the same steps I showed you in the video. This is exactly how
I personally learn new things. Also, I've carefully designed
tons of exercises that help you understand and remember the materials.
So make sure to do all these exercises, because the more you practice, the better you'll be
at Django or coding in general.
Welcome back to the Ultimate Django course. In this section,
we're going to talk about the basics of Django. First, I will give you a quick
introduction to what Django is and why it's so popular.
Then we'll talk about the fundamental web development concepts that every web
developer must know. Next, we'll set up our machine for development and
create our first Django project. Once that project is up and running,
I will show you two essential techniques for debugging Django applications.
This is going to be a short and sweet introduction to Django, so let's jump in and get started.
So what is Django and why is it so popular? Well, Django
is a free and open source framework for building web applications with
Python. It's not the only web framework for Python, but it's the most popular
one. Because it helps us build the website in less time with fewer
lines of code. That's why a lot of companies like YouTube, Instagram,
Spotify, and Dropbox use Django in their tech stack.
Now, Django is what we call a batteries included framework, which
means it comes with a lot of features out of the box so we don't have to
code them from scratch. For example, it gives us an admin interface for
managing our data which is a huge time saver, it also has an
object relational mapper that abstracts the database so we can query
or persist data without writing a lot of SQL code. It also comes
with an authentication package for identifying users, it also has a
package for caching data and much much more. So since Django
offers all these amazing features, we can focus on our application and its requirements.
We don't have to reinvent the wheel and code all these features from scratch.
Now, once in a while, you might come across someone like our popular
superstar developer, John Smith, who thinks Django is a piece of crap
because it's old and bloated with so many features. He used it, hated it,
and then rewrote his entire project with a new shiny framework that is
faster. Well, saying a framework is better than Django because it's faster
is kind of like saying a Ferrari is better than a truck because it's faster.
What if you want to move something? You're not going to use your Ferrari for that, right?
So a wise software engineer doesn't pick up a framework
merely based on its performance. There are so many other things you need to take into account
like the maturity of the framework, how stable it is from one version to another,
its learning curve, the size of the community and so on. Django
has been around for a long time and it has a huge community. So there are tons
of Django packages built by the community that you can reuse in your applications.
Also, if you get stuck, there's always someone out there to help you.
If you want to hire people, there are tons of people to choose from. So these are the benefits
of having a huge community around the framework. Now, regarding Django features,
yes, Django comes with a lot of features, but you don't have to use
or even learn all of them, because all these features are optional.
So you can use the features that make sense for your application. So in my opinion,
debates about the best framework in the world are useless. We all like
different things and just because someone doesn't like Django, it doesn't mean it's bad.
A lot of companies are using Django and are looking for Django developers.
Here in the US, the average salary of a Django developer is just over
$117,000 a year. So if you like Python and
want to get into web development, learning Django is a good investment for your future.
So, you learned that Django is a framework for building web
applications with Python. Now let's talk about some of the fundamental
concepts you need to understand to build web applications. Let's say we're going to
build an online store and publish it at mosh buy.com. Now this
website is going to have two parts or two applications. A front
end and a back end. The front end is the part that is loaded
inside a web browser on a client machine. It's the part that the user sees
and interacts with. The back end is the part that runs on a web server
and is responsible for data processing, validating business
rules and so on. Now let's imagine that Alice wants to visit our website.
So, she points her browser to mosh buy.com. This address
is also called a URL, which is short for uniform resource
locator. It's basically a way to locate a resource on our internet.
A resource can be a web page, an image, a video, a PDF
and so on. So, Alice types mosh buy.com in her browser and
presses enter. At this moment, her browser sends a request to the web
server that hosts our website and says, hey, Alice wants to see the
home page. So, the web server should take this request, process it,
and return a response back to the client. This data exchange is
defined by a protocol called HTTP, which is short for hyper text
transfer protocol. It defines how clients and servers can communicate.
So this is the big picture. As Alice navigates our website,
for each page, her browser sends an HTTP request to the server
and receives an HTTP response. Now, as part of building the back end
for this website, we need to decide how we're going to respond to clients.
One option is to generate the requested page on the server and return it to the client.
We use HTML for that. HTML is short for hyper text
markup language. It's a simple language for representing web pages
on their content. Every web page we have seen on our internet is built using HTML.
So one option is to generate the page on the server and return
an HTML document to the client. The other option is to return
only the data needed on the requested page and have the client generate
the page. So, instead of putting a complete page or
a complete HTML document in an HTTP response, we only return
the data like the list of products. Now what is the difference?
Well, if we push this responsibility to the client, we can free up the server
so it can serve more clients. Our application will be more scalable.
That's why over the past few years this approach has become more trendy and
is now considered the industry best practice. These days we have tools like
React, Angular, and Vue for generating web pages on the client.
These are all client side tools that are used by front end developers. In contrast,
we have server side tools for building back ends. Django falls
in this category. So you should not compare Django with let's say React.
You may compare Django with other server side frameworks like
ASP.NET Core which is used by C sharp developers, Express used by
JavaScript developers and so on. So if we push the responsibility
of generating web pages to the client, the server essentially becomes
a gateway to the data. On the server, we can provide endpoints
that the client can talk to to get or save various pieces of data.
For example, we can provide one endpoint to get the list of products
and another endpoint to get the list of orders someone has placed.
Now all these endpoints together represent the interface that clients
use to talk to the server. In technical terms, we say the server
provides an API or an application programming interface to clients.
This API is essentially like the buttons on a remote control.
All these buttons together represent the interface or the API we use to
interact with the TV. Okay? So in this course, our focus will
be on using Django to build an API for our online store. Client
applications can use this API to get or save the data. How
these clients are built is irrelevant here. We can use react, angular, or
even plain JavaScript. That falls under frontend development which has nothing to do
with Django. Once we build this API, if you know frontend development, you can
always build a client app that talks to this API. Alright, now that
you understand the big picture, we are ready to set up our development environment.
And that's what we will do next.
Alright, let's
make sure you have the right setup before we start coding. The first thing I want you to do is
upgrade your python to the latest version. So head over to python.org
slash download and download the latest version of python for your operating system.
Once you do that, then open up your terminal window and run
python dash dash version to make sure you have upgraded your python
correctly. Now here we see python 2.7 because on
mac we have two different versions of python running side by side. We have the old
python 2 which is now deprecated and we also have python
3. So if you're using a mac, you have to run python 3
dash dash version. But if you're on windows or linux you have to run
python dash dash version. So here I'm using python
3.9.5, great. Next we're going to use pip
or pip 3 if you're on mac, to install pip
n. I talked about pip n in my python course, it's basically a
dependency management tool for installing our application dependencies in
virtual environments. This way our application dependencies will not
clash with other applications dependencies. Okay, so
let's go ahead and install this.
Now in this course, just like my other courses, I'm going to use
visual studio code or vs code as my editor. It's just my personal preference.
If you have a preference for a different tool like pycharm, that's totally fine.
Having said that, I highly encourage you to use vs code, because throughout
the course I'm going to show you a lot of shortcuts and time saving tips that will
not apply to your editor. In case you don't have vs code, you can get it from
code.visualstudio.com. Now once you run it,
I want you to go to the extensions panel over here, and search
for python, make sure to install this extension
because with this we get features such as intellisense, debugging, code
navigation and so on.
Alright, now that we have installed all the necessary tools, let's create our first
Django project. So here in the terminal window, I'm going to go to my desktop,
you can go anywhere on your machine, it doesn't really matter, now
we're going to create a directory called storefront.
That is the name of our project. Next, we go inside this directory
and run pipenv install Django.
So we're going to install Django using pipenv inside a
virtual environment. Now, let's go ahead,
take a look, so over here
you can see that pipenv has created a virtual environment for this
project. Down below you can see the path to this virtual environment.
Now if you're on windows, you're going to see something like C drive backslash
whatever. Now if you're on a Mac and using z shell, which is this fancy
colorful terminal window, you can hold down the command key
and click on this path to go into it, otherwise you can just copy
this and use the cd command to go inside this directory.
Now take a look, so here's our virtual environment,
in this environment we have this bin folder that contains
a bunch of binaries, for example we have python, pip, Django
admin and so on. So back to the terminal, pipenv
created a virtual environment and installed Django inside that environment.
But in addition to this, pipenv also created two files
in this directory, pipfile and pipfile.log.
So I'm going to open this directory using visual studio code by running
code period. If this doesn't work on your machine, just drag and drop
this folder onto vs code. Alright,
so here's our pipfile, this is like package.json for JavaScript
projects. So in this file we can see that our project needs
this particular version of python, and under packages
you can see the packages that our application is dependent upon.
So here we have Django equals asterisk, that means any version
or the latest version of Django. If we installed a particular version
of Django, we would see that version here. Now back to the terminal
window, we need to activate this virtual environment, so we'll use the
python interpreter inside this virtual environment, not the one that is
installed globally on this machine. To do that we're going to run pipenv
shell. Okay, next
we're going to use Django admin to start a new project. Django
admin is a utility that comes with Django. So if you run it,
we can see all these commands that we can use to work with Django
projects. As we go through the course, you'll become familiar with these commands.
In this lesson we're going to use Django admin, start
project, and we're going to call that project store front.
Now back to vs code, Django
admin created this directory for our project, and inside this directory
it created another directory that is the core of our application.
In this directory we have these files which I'm going to talk about in a second, but before
I do so, let's get rid of this redundancy. Because we have three
store front directories. The top one is the one that we created
earlier in the terminal, and then we have these two other directories
one for the project, one for the core of our application. So
I'm going to delete this project directory,
now we're back in the previous step. So we don't have a Django project at this stage.
Now, back in the terminal, let's bring up the last command
but type a period at the end. This tells Django to use
the current directory as the project directory. So Django is not going to
create an additional directory for our project.
Now take a look. So, we have this directory
which is the core of our application. In this directory we have this init file
which defines this directory as a package, we have this settings module
where we define our application settings, we have the URLs module
where we define the URLs of our application, and these two other modules
that are used for deployment. For now, don't worry about them.
Now, next to this directory we have is file manage.py.
This is a wrapper around Django admin, so going forward
instead of Django admin we're going to use manage.py. The reason for this
is that manage.py takes the settings of this project into account.
Let me show you what I mean. So, now that we have a project
we want to run a web server. So, another command that Django admin
provides is run server.
However, if you're on Django admin, run server
we get an error saying request setting
debug, but settings are not configured because at this point
Django admin doesn't know about the settings of our project. So,
now that we have a project, instead of Django admin we're going to run
python manage.py, now look
we see the same commands that Django admin provides.
So, here we can say python manage.py
run server. Now, optionally we can supply a port
number, if we don't supply this, by default this will use port
8000. But you might have another application running on port 8000,
in that case you might want to explicitly set the port number. So,
let's go ahead with that, now we don't get an error, because manage.py
knows about the settings of our project. Now,
here we get this warning saying you have 18 unapplied migrations.
Don't worry about this yet, we'll talk about this soon. So, if you look
over here, you can see that Django has started a development server
at this address. So we can copy this and paste it into browser,
or if you're on a Mac and using z shell, you can hold down the command key
and click this. Alright, beautiful,
our first Django project is running successfully, so let's move on to the next lesson.
So far I've been using a separate terminal window, but vs code also has
an integrated terminal window that is easier to use, but to use that
we have to properly configure it to use the python interpreter inside
our virtual environment. Let me show you how to do this. So,
back to our terminal window, first we're going to stop the web server by pressing
ctrl and c. Now, back in vs code,
on the top, under the view menu, look,
we have this command palette, the shortcut on Mac is shift, command
and p. Now here we're going to search for python
interpreter. So, currently,
vs code is using this python interpreter that is installed globally on this
machine, we don't want to use this, we want to use the one inside our virtual environment.
But how can we find the path to our virtual environment? Very easy.
So, back to the terminal, let's run pip n
dash dash vn. Alright, here's the path
so let's copy this, good,
now back to vs code, we're going to select
interpreter path, then we're going to paste the path, and append
slash bin slash python
at the end. If you're on windows, instead of a forward slash, you have to
use a backslash. Good, now
in this project we have an extra directory vs code,
we have a settings file, and here we have the path to
python interpreter. Good. With this, we can go to the view menu,
now look, we have this integrated terminal,
the shortcut on Mac is control and backtick,
now vs code automatically activates the virtual environment
for this project. So, here we can run python
manage.py, run server. Good, so going
forward, I'm going to use the integrated terminal window here, it's easier,
we can always hide it by pressing control and backtick, or bring it
back, we can maximize it, move it around and so on.
Now one quick tip, sometimes when running this command, you might get a
syntax error saying invalid syntax. This happens every now and then
when vs code fails to activate the virtual environment for this project.
To solve this problem, all you have to do is open a new
terminal window, and look vs code executed this command
to activate the virtual environment for this project. Now we can run
python manage.py run server. Great.
Hey guys, Mosh here, I just wanted to let you know
that this tutorial you've been watching is actually the first hour of my
ultimate Django course. The complete course is about 10 hours and
goes way beyond this tutorial. So if you're serious about learning Django
and are looking for a job as a backend developer, I highly encourage you to
enroll in the course. The course comes with tons of exercises and solutions,
a full e-commerce project that you will eventually deploy to the cloud, plus
a 30 day money back guarantee and a certificate of completion you can add to your
resume. In case you're interested, I'll put the link down below. And if not,
that's totally fine, let's move on to the next lesson.
Alright,
let's talk about apps. So every Django project is essentially
a collection of various apps, each providing certain functionality.
Just like the apps on your mobile phone, each app provides a certain
functionality, right? Django projects are exactly the same. So
in this project, let's open up the store front directory, and then
look at our settings module. Now we can collapse this panel by pressing command
and B on Mac, or control and B on Windows. Okay, now
in this module, we have a bunch of different settings, in this lesson
we're going to look at the install apps. So every Django project
by default includes these apps. The first app is the
admin app, which gives us an admin interface for managing our data.
Then we have the auth app, which is used for authenticating
users, then we have content types app, which we'll talk about later in the course.
Next we have the sessions app, which is kind of legacy, we don't use sessions anymore.
A session is a temporary memory on the server for managing
users data. These days when building APIs with Django, we don't use
the sessions app. So we can come here and delete this app.
Then we have the messages app, which is used for displaying one time
notifications to the user, and finally we have the static files app
for serving static files, like images, CSS files and so on.
So each app provides a certain piece of functionality.
Now we can also create our own apps here. So let's save this file.
Now let's open up the terminal window by pressing control and back
tick. So here's our terminal window where we have our development
server running. We're going to open a new terminal window.
Okay, now let's expand this. To clear the window
we simply press control and L. Now we're going to run Python
manage.py, start app, and we're going to call this app
playground. Okay, so let's close
this window and open up the explorer panel. Alright,
look, here's our new app which is represented using a folder with a
special structure. So every Django app has the exact same structure.
Here we have the migrations folder for generating database tables,
we'll talk about that later in the course. We have a complete section about this topic.
We have the admin module where we define how the admin interface
for this app is going to look like. Next we have the apps module where
we configure this app. So the name is misleading. I don't know why Django
developers decided to call this module apps. It would be better if it was called
config. That's just my two cents. Next we have the models module where we define
the model classes for this app. We use model classes to pull out
data from the database and present to the user. Next we have the tests
module where we write our unit tests. And finally we have the views
module which we'll talk about in the next lesson. Again the name is misleading, this is
not the view that you think if you come from a frontend development background. So
what we have here is essentially a request handler. It's not a view, it doesn't have
a template or HTML. Again we'll talk about that in the next lesson.
So we created a new app, now we need to register this app in the
settings module. So, every time you create a new app,
you need to register it here in the list of installed apps. We simply
add the name of the app which is called playground.
Save the changes, done. In the next lesson we're going to talk about views.
Alright, let's talk about views. So
earlier you learned that HTTP is a request response protocol.
So every data exchange involves a request and a response. This is
where we use views in Django. So here in the playground folder,
let's open up the views module. This is where we define our
views or view functions. A view function is a function that
takes a request and returns a response. So more
accurately, it's a request handler. In some frameworks
it's called an action. In Django it's called a view. But I don't
agree with this name because from an architectural point of view, a view is often
associated with something that the user sees. That part in Django is called
a template and we'll talk about that later in this section. Now that aside, let's
create our first view function. So we're going to create a function
we can call it anything we want. I'm going to call it say
hello. Now this function should take a request object and
return a response. So first, on the top
from Django, that HTTP package, we're going to import
the HTTP response class. Now in this function we can
do anything we want. In a real world scenario we can pull data from a database
we can transform data, we can send emails and so on.
For now, let's just return a simple response. So we're
going to return an instance of the HTTP response
class, and in this object, in this response, you want to
add a simple string. So let's say hello world.
So this is our first view or first view function, now we need to
map this view to a URL, so when we get a request at that URL
this function will be called. And that's what we're going to do next.
Alright here's our Django project, now let's say
whenever we send a request to playground slash hello,
our view function should be called and return hello world to the user. Let's see
how we can do that. So back to our project, here in the playground folder
we're going to add a new file called URLs.py
you could call it anything, the name doesn't matter, but by convention we call it
URLs. Now in this module we're going to map our
URLs to our view functions. So on the top we're going to import
the path function from Django.URLs. So from
Django.URLs we're going to import the path function. Now don't worry about
memorizing any of these, as you practice all of this will become second nature.
Also, from the current folder we should import the
views module so we can reference our view function. Now we should define
a special variable called URL patterns. All in
lower case, make sure to spell it properly, because this is what Django looks for.
We should set this to an array of URL pattern
objects. We use the path function to create a URL pattern
object. So if we call this function, look at the signature of this function,
this function has a bunch of parameters, the first one is route, which is
a string, the notation you see here is called type annotation, which is kind of
a new feature in Python, with type annotation we can see the type of parameters
and the return value of a function. So the first parameter is route
which is a string, the second parameter is view, which is a function
that returns HTTP response object. Now look over here,
this notation represents the return type of this function.
So the path function returns a URL pattern object.
So I'm going to call this function and give it two arguments. A route or
a URL, which is playground slash hello, and
a view function. So from the views module we're going to get
say hello. Note that I'm not calling this function so here
we don't have a pair of parenthesis, we're just passing a reference to this function.
Okay, so what we have here is called
a URL conf module, that basically means URL configuration.
So every app can have its own URL configuration. But
now we need to import this URL configuration into the main URL configuration
for this project. Where is it? You saw it earlier.
So, back to the explorer panel, here in the store front folder,
we have another URLs module.
Up here we have a bunch of comments about how we should use this module,
now look over here. If you want to include another URL conf
there are two things we need to do. First we need to import the include function
from Django.URLs, so over here we have from Django.URLs
we're going to import the include function.
Next we need to add a URL to URL patterns.
So in this module, we also have a URL patterns object
which is an array of URL patterns object. So here we're going to call
paths, give it a route, and then we use
the include function to reference the URL configuration module
in this app. So
we're going to call paths and say any URLs
that start with playground, followed by a forward slash
should be routed to our playground app. So this is where we use
the include function. Now, the include function requires a parameter
that is a string, here we're going to reference playground.
URLs. So if we send a request
to playground slash hello, Django
knows that all requests that start with playground should be handled by this
app, so it's going to chop off the first part of this URL
and pass the rest to the URL configuration module
in the playground app. So back to this URLs module
we no longer need to add playground here because we added it once
in the main URL configuration module. So we simply
add hello, followed by a forward slash, I forgot to add that. We always
end our route with a forward slash. So let's save the changes
now, whenever we change our code, Django web server
automatically restores itself. So let's open up the terminal window
make sure we don't have any errors, good, so back to the
browser, let's send a request to this endpoint. Great, we see
hello world on the screen. So this is how we can map URLs to
view functions. Next we're going to talk about templates.
So I told you that views in Django are not really views
they're more like request handlers or actions. What we often call a view
in other frameworks is called a template in Django. So let's see how
we can use a template to return HTML content to the client.
So here in the playground app, we're going to add
a new folder called templates, and in this folder
we're going to add a new file called hello.html.
And of course we could call it anything. Here we can write some HTML markup
for example we can type h1 and press tab to add an h1
heading and say hello world. Don't worry if you don't know
HTML we're not going to use it in this course. I just want to show you how Django
templates work. So let's save the changes. Now
back to our view function, instead of returning a plain
HTTP response, we're going to use the render function to render a
template and return HTML markup to the client. So let's
remove this line and call the render function. Now
look at the return type of this function. It returns
an HTTP response object. So here we're going to
return the response. Now let's remove the brackets and type them again
so we can see the function signature. The first parameter here
is a request object and the type of this
is HTTP request. So we're going to pass this request
object right here. Now the second
parameter, that's the name of our template, which is a string.
So here I'm going to say hello.html
the other parameters are optional so don't worry about them at this point. Now
save the changes, let's make sure our project works up to this point.
So back in the browser, refresh, beautiful, now we see
HTML content. We can verify it by right clicking on this page and
looking at the page source, so look, we're returning
HTML content. Great. Now let's make this a bit more
interesting. So back to our template, instead of hello world
we can dynamically render some value. So back to our
view function, let's type a comma to see the next parameter.
That is a context object and the type of
this is a mapping of string to any. That means
we can pass any mapping object that maps a string value
to any other type of object. So here we can pass a dictionary.
So let's pass a dictionary, the type of the key
should be a string so we can call that name and we're going to set that to a value
like let's say mosh. Now back to our template
instead of hello world we can render
the name that we passed here. So we type two pairs of braces
and in between we type the name of the key.
Save, refresh, beautiful. Now
in this template we can also write some logic. So
we can type an if statement. So we type braces and in between them
we add two percentage signs, in between
them we can write an if statement. So we can say if name is set
we can render it here, otherwise
we can render hello
world. And of course we need an end if clause as well.
So end if. Now this syntax is kind of ugly
but the good thing about Django is that it's modular, so you can easily
replace Django's default template engine with your preferred template
engine. But once again, we don't really use templates in Django projects
that often these days. There are special cases for them, but for the most
part, we use Django to build APIs that return data, not
HTML content. So I just included this lesson so you know what
templates are and how they work. We're not going to spend any more time on templates for
now unless we encounter a situation where we really need them.
Let's talk about debugging Django
applications in vs code. This is particularly useful if our application
doesn't produce the right result and we want to run it line by line and see
where exactly something has gone wrong. So click on this icon
to open the run and debug panel. Now the first time you see
this message saying we should create a launch.json file.
Basically we need to create a launch profile so vs code knows how to run
or debug this application. So let's click on this,
now in this list, select Django,
alright, here's our launch.json file, what you see here is kind of like a dictionary
in Python. You have a bunch of key value pairs. These
key value pairs define a launch profile. So vs code knows
that to run this application, it should use the current Python
interpreter to run manage.py which exists
in our workspace folder and as an argument, it should
pass run server to it. Here we can add an additional
argument to specify the port so it doesn't
slash with port 8000 which is currently in use. Save the changes,
we're done with this file, so let's close it.
Now if you're curious, let me show you where this file exists.
It's added to our project up here inside
the vs code folder. So here's our launch profile. Now that we
have a launch profile, if we go to the run and debug panel,
we see something else. So here we can start our application for debugging,
but before doing so, I want to write some dummy code here in our view function.
So, let's set x to 1 and y to 2.
Now, I'm going to click on this line to insert a
breakpoint. When we add a breakpoint, vs code will execute
every line of code until it hits our breakpoint. From that point
onward, we can execute our code line by line. So
let's add a breakpoint, and then start the application for
debugging.
Alright, let me collapse this window, good. So
in this new terminal window, we have a development server listening
on port 9000, so let's hold down the command key on mac or
control on windows and click on this link. Alright, here's what we
get, the homepage of our project is gone because we have registered a custom
route, that is playground slash hello. So we see the homepage
only the first time we run our Django project. So, let's go to
playground slash hello. Alright, our breakpoint
is activated and we are on this line. Now on the left side
in the variable section, you can see the local variables, so
currently we have the request object, that is the request object that we receive
in this function, so we can expand it and inspect
its various attributes. We don't want to do that for now, so
let's close this, we want to execute our code line by line.
So here we have a bunch of functions, the first one is step over
and the shortcut for this is f10, with this we can step
over the current line, so if we press f10,
this line gets executed and now we are on the second line. Now look over
here, in the list of local variables we have x and its value
is 1. This is very useful when debugging applications, so
if something is not calculated properly, we can inspect it here.
Now most of the time you can see your local variables here, but if not
you can always add them in the watch window. So before recording this video
I was practicing, that's why you see x here, let me select
this and delete it. So in your watch section you're not going to have any
variables, to add one, simply click on this and then type
the name of our variable. So this is how
we can step over various lines, so we can press f10 again, and again
so this function is executed and now back in the browser
we see the final result. Now let's do something more interesting.
So back to our code, let's close the terminal window
so we have more space, I'm going to define a function here
called calculate, and here we're going to set x to 1
y to 2 and return x. Just some dummy code.
Now over here, we're going to call the calculate function.
Okay, now save the changes,
back in the browser, let's refresh, so our view function
gets called. Now we are right here. Now this time instead of stepping
over this line, we want to step into it. Because if you step over this line
we're not going to see what happened in the calculate function.
We see the final result, so we see x is set to 1
and we can verify that over here as well. But sometimes we need to
step into a function to see what is happening there. Maybe there is a bug
inside the calculate function. So, let's restart
the debugger, okay,
I'm going to close this, back in the browser, let's refresh this
page, okay, we're back
to this line, now this time we're going to step into this function. So look
over here, this is the icon for stepping into a function, and
as you can see the shortcut is f11. So if you press f11
we go inside the calculate function. Now
we can execute each line using f10 or step over
and see where something has gone wrong. Now let's imagine this calculate function
is a large function with a lot of code. At some point you want to step out of it
without having to execute every line of code in this function.
There's a shortcut for this. So, look over here,
that is step out. The shortcut is shift and f11.
So if you press shift and f11, we get back to the
previous function. So this is how we can debug Django applications in
vs code. Now, once we're done, it's always a good practice
to remove these breakpoints, otherwise they get in the way. So as you
debug your applications, you place various breakpoints in different parts of your code
and you'll hit them all the time. So always remove your breakpoints
once you're done with them. So we're done with this debugging session, now
we can disconnect by pressing shift and f5 or
click on this icon. Alright, now one last
tip before we finish this lesson. On the top, under the run menu,
look, we have a command called run without
debugging. The shortcut on Mac is control and f5.
So if we use this shortcut, we can start our application without having to
run python manage.py run server. Let me show you what
I mean. So, first let's bring up our terminal window.
Here's the second terminal window that we used for debugging. I'm going to
delete this. Here's the first terminal window where we started
our application by running python manage.py run server.
So let's press control and c to stop the server.
Good, I'm also going to delete this terminal window. Let's imagine we just
open this project in vs code. Day 1. Now to run this
application without debugging, we can press control and f5.
Now our application has started
on port 9000. So we can go to this address and
then hit playground slash hello.
So this is how we can run our application without debugging. Just remember that
if you use this command, your breakpoints are not going to get hit. So if you
want to debug your applications, you should start it in the debug mode.
There is another way to debug Django
applications using a powerful tool called Django debug toolbar.
So if you go to Google and search for Django debug toolbar,
you're going to find this page. Over here you're going to find
the installation instructions. So I highly encourage you to follow along with me
and repeat the same steps so we install this toolbar together.
So, first we have to use pip or pip env to install
Django debug toolbar. So back to vs code,
I'm going to open up a new terminal window, and
as you can see vs code used the source command to activate our virtual environment.
So now, let's run pip env install
Django dash debug dash toolbar.
Good.
Now, back to the documentation, the next step is to add
debug toolbar in the list of installed apps in our settings module.
So, back to vs code, we can press command
and p on mac or control and p on windows to bring up the search box.
Now we search for our settings module. Good.
Now in the list of installed apps, at the end we're going to add
debug underline toolbar. Good.
Now, the next step. The next step is to add a new
URL pattern in our main URL conf module. So I'm going to
copy this line and back to vs code,
let's bring up the URLs module, we're going to pick the one in the store front
folder. Okay, now we add a comma here and
paste that line. Now here we have a compilation error, because
debug toolbar is a module that we have to import on the top. So if you look at the
documentation, you can see that over here, import
debug toolbar. So copy this and paste it right here.
Good. Now back to the documentation. The next step is to
add a middleware. We use middleware to hook into Django's request
response processing. So in our settings module we have a setting
for middleware, we're going to add this line
in that file. So copy this, back to the settings module,
here we have the install apps, right after that you can see the middleware
setting. So we're going to add that on the top.
Now the final step is to add our IP address
in the internal IP setting. So for local development
we should use 127.0.0.1. So I'm going to copy this
entire setting, because by default this doesn't exist in a new Django project,
so copy this, and I'm going to paste it
anywhere in this settings file, it doesn't really matter. Okay, save,
so we have completed all the steps, now back in the browser, if you
go to this URL, playground slash hello, we don't see the toolbar
it should appear here, because the toolbar only appears when we return
a proper HTML document. If you right click here and look at the
page source, you can see that we are not returning a proper HTML document.
So we don't have the HTML head and body elements.
So let's open up hello.html, now on the top
we type HTML, press tab, inside these elements we're going to
add a body, and then inside the body
we're going to add the code that we had earlier. So let's move that right here,
good, now we have a proper HTML
document, of course the head element is missing but it doesn't really matter.
Now back to the browser, refresh, and here's Django debug toolbar.
Here we have different panels like history, we're seeing the URLs we have hit
so far, we have versions, to see the version of Django, Python
and debug toolbar we're running, we have processing time, we have
our settings, we have request headers and so on. Now my personal
favorite panel is the SQL or SQL panel.
Here we can see the queries that are sent to the database, so later in the course
where we talk about querying the database using Django's object relational
mapper, we're going to come back to this panel and see what queries Django
will generate and send to the database. So that's it for this lesson,
we're done with this section, in the next section we're going to talk about building
a data model. So I'll see you in the next section.
Welcome back to another section of the ultimate
Django course. In this section, we're going to talk about models
which are used to store and retrieve data. We'll start off by a quick
introduction to data modeling to make sure you know the essential concepts, then
we're going to design the data model for an ecommerce application, next we're going to
talk about organizing our models in apps to improve reusability,
this is one of the areas that is often misunderstood so I'm going to demystify
it once and for all. And then we'll spend the rest of this section in coding model
classes. We'll use these classes to store and retrieve data throughout
the course. So let's jump in and get started.
The first step in every Django project
is figuring out the pieces of data we want to store. So
what entities or concepts do we have in an ecommerce application?
Well, for starters we need the concept of a product with attributes like
title, description, price, and inventory. Now in a real
scenario, a product entity might have other attributes, it really depends
on the requirements of our application. For now, we just want to keep things simple.
Now, quite often our products are divided in different categories
like shoes, beauty products, fruits, and so on. So we need
another entity called collection or category with an attribute called
title. Now we need to add a relationship or an association
between these entities so we can start from one end and navigate to the other end.
For example, we can get a collection and find all the products in that
collection. Now let's assume that in our application, a
product can belong to one and only one collection, and a collection
can have multiple products. So an asterisk represents
many. We could also use an n here. Now we have a one to
many relationship between collection and product. So, relationships
can be one to one, one to many, and many to many. Back to our
diagram. Now over here we can add a label called products, and that means
when we code these entities or these classes in the collection class
we're going to have an attribute called products. For now, I just want to hide this
for simplicity. Now, sometimes we can have multiple relationships
or multiple associations between two entities. So let's
imagine that a collection can optionally have a featured product.
That is the product whose picture we want to show to the user.
So we can add a second relationship between these entities. Now look at this number here.
0 to 1 means a collection can have 0 to
1 product and we're going to call that attribute featured product.
So once again, that means in the collection class we're going to have an attribute
called featured product. Now you might ask, what about the
id attribute? Shouldn't every entity have an id attribute? Yes.
But Django is going to automatically create that for us, that's why I haven't shown it here.
Now a little exercise for you. Grab a piece of paper
and identify the other essential entities we need in an e-commerce
application. Just the bare minimum. Don't go ahead and create a complex
diagram like this, I don't want this. There are only 5 entities that I want you
to identify. So spend a couple minutes and identify these entities
along with the attributes and relationships. Then come back and see my solution.
Alright, so this is what we ended up with in the previous lesson.
We have a one to many relationship between collections and products.
Now don't take this as a hard and fast rule. Maybe in your
application, a product can belong to many collections. Then you're going to have
a many to many relationship between products and collections.
So, back to our model. I'm going to remove the collection from here, so
we have some free space on the screen. Now, what else do we need here?
Well, in every e-commerce application, we have the concept of a shopping
cart, right? So we're going to have an entity or a model or class called
cart with an attribute called created at. Let's assume
that we need to know when each cart is created, so every now and then we can
do a clean up and remove carts that are 30 days old. I just
made this up. But in a real scenario, you should always design your models
based on the requirements of your project. Don't make up your own rules.
Now, we need a relationship or an association between products
and carts. Because a cart can have multiple products, and a product might be
in different carts. So here we have a many to many relationship between
products and carts. Now, sometimes the relationship between two entities
can have attributes. For example, if a product is in a shopping cart,
we need to know how many instances of that product we have in the shopping cart.
So this relationship itself should have an attribute called
quantity. So we're going to add a new entity here called cart item.
Now look at the notation I've used to represent this concept. I've
connected cart item to the relationship using a dashed line. That means
cart item represents the relationship between these two entities.
Product and cart. This is what we call an association class.
So cart item is an association class.
Now there's another way to show this. Instead of using an association class,
we can add a relationship between cart and cart item, because a cart
might contain multiple items, and an item belongs to one
and only one cart. Similarly we can add a relationship
between product and cart item, because each cart item represents
a single product, and a product might be referenced by many
cart items. So here we have two one to many relationships
between these entities. Now compare this with the association class
notation. So we can either add a many to many relationship
with an association class, or two one to many relationships.
It's a matter of personal preference. So we're done with the shopping
cart, but you might ask, what about the user or the customer that owns
this cart? Where is that in the diagram? Well I haven't connected cart with
an entity like customer, because we don't want to force people to register and
log in before they can add products to their shopping cart, okay? So there is
no relationship between carts and customers. So carts are essentially
anonymous. Anyone can have a cart, whether they're anonymous users or
registered customers. So, we're done with the cart,
now let's talk about customers. So our customer entity can have attributes
like name, email, username, password, and so on. Now for
simplicity, I'm only showing name and email here. Now a customer
can have many orders, and each order belongs to one
and only one customer. So we need a one to many relationship between
customers and orders. Now once again, the order entity might have multiple
attributes, for now we just want to know when this order was placed.
Now an order can contain multiple products, and a product
can be in multiple orders. So we have a many to many relationship between orders
and products. And similar to the shopping cart example, this relationship
itself needs attributes. So here we need another entity called order item
with an attribute called quantity. That's our association class.
Alternatively, you could add a relationship between order and order
item, because each order may contain multiple items, and
each order item belongs to one and only one order.
Similarly, an order item references one and only one product,
while a given product might be referenced by multiple order items.
So two, one to many relationships. So these are the entities
that I wanted you to identify. But to make this project more interesting, I
decided to throw in one more entity, tag. Here we have a many to many
relationship between products and tags, because a product can have many
tags, and a tag might be referenced by different products. We'll come back to this
entity in the next lesson.
So I told you
that a Django project contains one or more apps, and just like the apps on your
phone, each app in a Django project provides a specific piece of
functionality. So that means each app is going to have its own
data model. So in this lesson, we're going to look at a few different ways to organize
our entities in different apps. One way is to have a single app called
the store, and drop all of our entities here. Now, we can bundle and
distribute this app via pip, and this way anyone can install this app
in their project and get all these models and the functionality around them.
So next time we're working on an ecommerce project, we don't have to rewrite the same
functionality over and over. We simply install this app in our project,
and write extra code for customization. Great. But there's a problem
here. As this application grows and gets more complex,
it gets bloated with too many things. Like too many models, too many
views and other stuff. This is what we call a monolith, like a large
heavy piece of stone. So at some point our application might become
hard to understand, hard to maintain, and hard to reuse. It becomes like one of
those remote controls with too many buttons. When designing these apps, we want
to follow the Unix philosophy. So each app should do one thing
and do it well. So here's another solution. We can break down
this project into four small apps. The products app, which represents
a product catalog. So here we're going to have three entities, product,
collection, and tag. Then we're going to have the customers app for
managing customers, we're going to have the shopping cart app for adding
the shopping cart functionality, and the orders app for adding the ordering
functionality. Not bad, right? Well, this is actually a poor
way of breaking down this project for a number of reasons. Look at the coupling
or dependency between these apps. The orders app is dependent on the
shopping cart app, which is dependent on the products app. So next time
we're working on an ecommerce project, we'll have to install all these apps one
by one. First we have to install the products app, followed by the shopping
cart app, the customers app, and the orders app. Ideally each app
should be self contained so we can easily drop it into a new project.
The other problem is that if we publish a new version of the products app,
that might cause a break and change in the shopping cart and subsequently
orders apps. So anyone using these apps have to upgrade all these apps
together. Again, more and more work. Also, it doesn't really make
sense to have the shopping cart functionality without having a product catalog.
Right? Why would we ever want to add the shopping cart functionality to a project
without a product catalog. So shopping cart functionality
and product catalog always go together. By the same token,
why would we ever want to add the shopping cart functionality to a project without
the ability to place an order? Just to allow people to add something to their
shopping cart? Then what? Again, it doesn't really make sense.
So these concepts are highly related and should be bundled together.
If we separate them, we increase coupling between apps and we end up with the
problems I just talked about. So does it mean we have to go back to the monolithic
design? No. There is a middle ground here. Look at the tag entity.
The ability to tag products is optional. We don't necessarily need it
in every ecommerce application. In fact, we might need it in other
types of applications like a blog or video platform and so on.
So tagging is not specific to products or an ecommerce application.
It's a separate piece of functionality. So I'm going to move
the tag entity to a separate app called tags. And here we're going to have
another entity called tagged item which represents an item
that is tagged. It can be a product, an article, a video and so on.
It's an abstract concept. Now with this separation, each
app is self contained and provides a specific piece of functionality.
So we can use either or both of them in a new project depending on
what we're going to build. Plus we have zero coupling between these apps,
so we can independently change and deploy them without affecting other
apps. This is the proper way to break down this project into multiple
apps. So here's the take away. If our app boundary is so
large, we'll end up with a monolith that gets bloated and becomes hard to
reuse. On the other hand, if our app boundaries are so small and
fine grained, we'll end up with a lot of coupling between them. A good
design is one with minimal coupling and high cohesion meaning high
focus. So each app is focused on a specific piece of functionality and
includes everything needed to fulfill that piece of functionality.
So back to vs code, we're going to create two new apps.
So we run python manage.py start
app, the first app is store, and the
second one is tags. Okay, now
as I told you before, every time we create a new app, we should add it in the list
of installed apps. So let's close this window and
go to our settings module, here's the list of installed apps,
I'm going to add those apps right here. So store and
tags. Alright, we're done with this step, starting from
the next lesson, we're going to create the model classes for these apps.
Hey guys, Mosh here. I just wanted to let you know that
this tutorial you've been watching is actually the first hour of my ultimate
Django course. The complete course is about 10 hours and goes
way beyond this tutorial. So if you're serious about learning Django and
are looking for a job as a backend developer, I highly encourage you to enroll in the course.
The course comes with tons of exercises and solutions, a full
e-commerce project that you will eventually deploy to the cloud, plus a
30 day money back guarantee and a certificate of completion you can add to your resume.
In case you're interested, I've put the link down below. So thank you for
watching and I hope to see you in the course.